MUAZZAM NASHAT

Atlanta, GA | 646.897.1746 | muazzamhc.nashat@gmail.com | GitHub | LinkedIn | Blog

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

Versatile full-stack software developer with experience in Ruby on Rails and JavaScript (React/Redux) based programming with a background in data analysis. I found my passion for coding during graduate school while taking data mining classes and building predictive models using various statistical tools. With my four years of experience as a data analyst and research assistant, I developed an analytical and problem-solving mindset that translates beautifully to writing efficient and readable code.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Proficient: Ruby on Rails, JavaScript, ReactJS, Redux, PostgreSQL, SQLite, JSON, STATA, R, SAS

Exposure: Python, Heroku, Google Cloud, AWS, HTML5, CSS, Git, Test (RSpec, Mocha), Bootstrap, Sinatra

TECHNICAL PROJECTS

FinAdvisor - GitHub Front-end / Back-end | Demo | Live

A Single Page Application (SPA) that lets users track their expenses.

Technologies: ReactJS, Rails, Material-UI, JWT Web token

- Utilized Material-UI framework to build the front-end.
- Implemented user authentication using JWT web token.
- Integrated Redux store to store, update and persist data throughout the application.
- Used react-router to implement proper RESTful routing.
- Utilized Redux thunk middleware to handle asynchronous web requests.

iGram - GitHub | Demo | Live

An Instagram clone with post, comment, like and follow features.

Technologies: Rails, jQuery, Bootstrap

- Utilized Devise gem for user authentication and authorization.
- Implemented Facebook login feature with Omniauth-Facebook rails gem.
- Applied RESTful design principles for CRUD functionality with nested routes.
- Utilized Rails' active record validation to preserve data persistency.

Yap - GitHub Front-end / Back-end | Demo | Live

A Single Page Application (SPA) that lets users view, create and read reviews about different restaurants.

Technologies: Rails, Vanilla JS, Bootstrap

- Developed a Rails API with endpoints for users, restaurants, reviews.
- Built the front-end activity and user experience with pure JavaScript.
- Implemented search and sorting features and utilized event handlers and DOM manipulation to show correct results.
- Integrated Google places and photos APIs to let users find restaurants and attach pictures to reviews.

StockTracker - GitHub | Demo | Live

A web app built to follow stock prices, read latest news and see stock recommendations from analysts with real time data.

Technologies: Ruby, Sinatra framework

- Applied the MVC pattern to build the app using Ruby Sinatra framework.
- Used active record to validate unique users to prevent duplicate data.
- Utilized 'bcrypt' gem to hash and salt passwords for secure implementation of user authentication.
- Integrated an API to fetch real-time stock data to show price, news and analyst recommendation.

EXPERIENCE

Central Michigan University - Economics Department Research Assistant

Mount Pleasant, MI 01/2018 - 01/2020

- Built a salary prediction model for National Hockey League players using SAS Enterprise Miner, a statistical tool. Performed data partition, imputation, variable selection techniques to prepare the data, and selected the best model based on the lowest average square error.
- Performed Linear regression and Logistic regression on panel data of almost 30,000 people to find a relationship between health and income using STATA. Coded macro variables in SAS to clean and merge the
- Analyzed 450,000 transactions of a superstore to find an association between items purchased from two departments and found that people who buy perfume will be 3.6 times more likely to buy toothbrush than a random purchase using SAS Enterprise Miner.

Amity Education BD

Sylhet, Bangladesh, South Asia 02/2016 - 11/2017

Data Analyst

- Used STATA and Microsoft SQL Server to analyze data and presented the reports to the stockholders in a non-technical way.
- Analyzed trends in the data and reported the Return on Investment (ROI) by showing how performance achieved business goals.
- Evaluated clients' data and sales information to better prepare managerial action and strategy. Increased sales by 30% by presenting key marketing strategies.

EDUCATION

Flatiron School Full Stack Web Development, Ruby on Rails and JavaScript program 08/ 2020 - 01/2021

Central Michigan University

Mount Pleasant, MI 01/2018 - 01/ 2020

MA in Economics with a 3.91 GPA SUST

Sylhet, Bangladesh, South Asia 01/2014 - 01/ 2015

MSS in Economics BSS in Economics

01/2009 - 01/2013

Online